Register of the Willy Achim Fiedler papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Willy Achim Fiedler papers
1933-1998
95009
Hoover Institution Archives
16 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 3 oversize folders (9.1 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, notes, memoranda, technical reports, patent applications, clippings, other printed matter, video tape, sound recording, and photographs relating to the German missile development program during World War II, including the "V1," and to postwar American missile development programs, especially the Polaris missile and other submarine launched ballistic missiles.
Fiedler, Willy Achim, 1908-1998.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of all video recordings in this collection are available for immediate access. To listen to sound recordings during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1995.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1908 January 23 Born, Freudenstadt, Black Forest, Germany
1934 June 1 Received Diplom-Ingenieur (Master of Engineering) from the Technical University, Stuttgart
1935-1936 Designer for the British Aircraft Manufacturing Co. Ltd. in Feltham, England
1937 November 16 Received the title of Flugbaumeister (aeronautical engineer) from the Institute for Aviation Research (Deutsche Versuchsanstalt für Luftfahrt, DVL) in Berlin
1938-1944 Designer and test pilot at the Gerhard Fieseler Aircraft Works in Kassel, Germany
1942-1944 Tester of the "V1" missile for Gerhard Fieseler in Peenemünde, Germany
1945 January-May Co-owner and technical director for the Bachem Company in Waldsee, Germany
1945 October-1948 May Owner and manager of Ingenieurbureau Fiedler in Nabern, Germany
1948-1956 Worked at the U.S. Naval Air Missile Test Center (NAMTC) in Point Mugu, California, as part of Operation Paperclip
1954 January 27 Received the Distinguished Civilian Service Award from the U.S. Navy
1956 Began work at Lockheed Missiles and Space Company in Sunnyvale, California
1958 Became chief scientist at Lockheed Missiles and Space Company
1973 Retired from Lockheed Missiles and Space Company
1998 January 17 Died, Los Altos Hills, California
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, scientific writings, experiment notes, memoranda, technical reports, patent applications, clippings, other printed matter, video tape, sound recording, and photographs relating to the German missile development program during World War II, including the "V1," and to postwar American missile development programs, especially the Polaris missile and other submarine launched ballistic missiles. The bulk of the collection relates to these and various other scientific studies and experiments that Fiedler conducted in the decades after his immigration to the United States, organized into a Career File.
World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations.; World War, 1939-1945--Germany.; Polaris (Missile); United States. Navy--Weapons systems.; Lockheed Missiles and Space Company.; Nuclear weapons.; Engineers.
- Biographical File, 1937-1998
  - Identification cards, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Drawing of Fiedler, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Family tree, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - "Black Forest Love Song,", undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Arranged and translated into English by Fiedler.
  - Resumes and academic papers, 1937-1995 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    Includes photographs of Fiedler's Diplomarbeit, an entry for "Who's Who in Science and Engineering," and his personal notes on his fleet ballistic missile development experience. In English and German.
  - Awards, 1948-1979 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Legal documents, 1948-1954 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Oxnard house design, 1948-1956 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    Financial and legal materials, and notes, related to the design and construction of Fiedler's home in Oxnard, California. See also: Oversize Materials/Large blueprints.
  - Memorial programs and obituary, 1998 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1952-1986 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    In English and German.
  - Miscellaneous personal notes, 1956-1986 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Appointment books, 1960-1965 (Box-folder 1: 12-16)
  - Appointment books, 1966-1973 (Box-folder 2: 1-8)
- Correspondence, 1945-1995
  - Not written to or by Fiedler, 1948-1966, undated (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Unidentified, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - General, 1948-1959, undated (Box-folder 2: 11-12)
  - General, 1961-1995 (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
  - Akademische Fliedergruppe Stuttgart, 1982-1993 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Bachem, Erich, 1948-1956, undated (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Barker, Lawrence Jr., 1987-1989 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Barker, William A., 1987-1992 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Baur, Isolde, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Baur, Karl, 1948-1955 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Behrenbeck, 1948-1951, undated (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Billings, Anne, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Bollay, William, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Brown, Robert E., 1953-1954 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Bussenius-Kraft, Ruth, 1949-1960 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Daggett, Max, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - De Roos, Willem, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Diehl, Walter S., 1948-1952 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Ehemaligen Peenemünder, 1980 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - Eiss, Liselotte, 1948-1951, undated (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Erb, Theo, 1951 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Fiedler, Gertrud, 1989-1994, undated (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - Fiedler, Herbert and Tilly, 1991-1992, undated (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - Fiedler, Karl, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - Fiedler, Monika, 1991-1992, undated (Box-folder 3: 23)
  - Fiedler, Petra, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 3: 24)
  - Fieseler, Gerhard, 1967-1977 (Box-folder 3: 25)
  - Flessner, Heinz, 1979 (Box-folder 3: 26)
  - Freitag, Robert F., 1955-1994 (Box-folder 3: 27)
  - Griehl, Manfred, 1987 (Box-folder 3: 28)
  - Grimm, Hans, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 3: 29)
  - Guter, Frank, undated (Box-folder 3: 30)
  - Helga and Ernst, 1992 (Box-folder 3: 31)
  - Hellmold, Wilhelm, 1980-1993 (Box-folder 3: 32)
  - Hensel, Manfred, 1979-1986 (Box-folder 3: 33)
    See also: photograph of Fiedler and Hensel in Box 16, Folder 12.
  - Hirth, Wolf, 1949-1951 (Box-folder 3: 34)
  - Hoerner, Sighard F., 1949-1969 (Box-folder 3: 35)
  - Hohmann, B. A., 1950 (Box-folder 3: 36)
  - Hutzel, Hans, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 3: 37)
  - Ilse, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 3: 38)
  - Jones, Walter R., 1953-1956 (Box-folder 3: 39)
  - Karin, 1986 (Box-folder 3: 40)
  - Kitchen, Larry O., 1986, undated (Box-folder 3: 41)
  - Klaus, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 3: 42)
    Includes letter to Fiedler's wife, Grete.
  - Klein, Gerald, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 3: 43)
  - Knapp, Werner, 1994 (Box-folder 3: 44)
  - Kössler, Karl, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 3: 45)
  - Krauss, Hanns, 1946-1950 (Box-folder 3: 46)
  - Lahde, Reinhard and Hildegard, 1993, undated (Box-folder 3: 47)
  - Leo, 1984 (Box-folder 3: 48)
  - Lutz-Fiedler, Hedwig, 1945-1992 (Box-folder 3: 49)
    Includes letters from Fiedler's wife, Grete.
  - Marquardt, Karen and Jana, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 3: 50)
  - Mayer, Max, 1995 (Box-folder 3: 51)
  - Middelmann-Motz, J. J. and Astrid V., 1991-1993 (Box-folder 3: 52)
  - Middlebrook, Martin, 1980 (Box-folder 3: 53)
  - National Air and Space Museum, 1974-1984 (Box-folder 3: 54)
  - Niethammer, Hellmut, 1987-1991 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Northrup Aircraft, Inc., 1951-1955 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Petrikat, Kurt, 1948-1950 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Priewe, Gerd D., 1980 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Proppe, Tasso, 1948-1994 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Quenzler, H. H. W., 1988-1991 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Rathjen, Walter, 1985 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Rees, Eberhard F. M., 1948-1952 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Riedel, Peter, 1985 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Röhm, Ludwig, 1948-1953 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Root, L. E., 1959-1965 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Schemp, Martin, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Segebrecht, Willfried, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Steuer, Herbert, 1949-1951 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Steurer, Heike, 1992, undated (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Steurer, Martin, 1991-1992, undated (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Steurer, Rudolf, 1948-1950, undated (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Stüwe, Botho, 1987 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Von Köhn, Siegfried D., 1982 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Walter, Wilhelm, 1948-1953 (Box-folder 4: 20)
- Career File, 1936-1994
  - Projects
    Notes, studies, experiments, drafts, graphs, figures, technical reports, memos, and secondary printed material related to the various construction and research projects Fiedler was involved in, grouped by place of employment.
    - British Aircraft Manufacturing Co. Ltd., 1936 (Box-folder 4: 21)
      See also: Oversize Material/Large blueprints.
    - Gerhard Fieseler Werke
      - Maps of grounds, undated (Box-folder 4: 22)
      - Unknown projects, 1937-1940, undated (Box-folder 4: 23)
      - Fi 156 "Storch,", 1938-1994 (Box-folder 4: 24)
      - Fi 99 "Jung-Tiger,", 1938 (Box-folder 4: 25)
      - Fi 256 "Super-Storch,", 1981-1990 (Box-folder 4: 26)
        See also: photograph in Box 16, Folder 12.
      - Fi 103 "V-1,", 1945-1994, undated (Box-folder 4: 27)
      - Reichenberg Project, 1945-1985 (Box-folder 4: 28)
        See also: Oversize Material/Large diagrams. In English and German.
    - Bachem Werke, 1978-1985, undated (Box-folder 4: 29)
      Material about the Bachem Ba 349A "Natter." In German and Italian.
    - Ingenieurbureau Fiedler, 1947-1954 (Box-folder 4: 30)
      Ledgers, bills, and other papers related to the running of Fiedler's furniture business and its merge with Kombi-Möbel in 1948.
    - Naval Air Missile Test Center (NAMTC)
      - Employment, 1948-1959 (Box-folder 4: 31)
        Includes invitee list for NAMTC 50th anniversary reunion in 1991.
      - Projects, 1948-1955 (Box-folder 4: 32)
        Includes materials on Project CROW, the Loon Missile, and Regulus I. See also: photographs of the Loon and Regulus missiles in Box 16, Folder 6.
      - Pacific Missile Range Advisory Board, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 4: 33)
      - Printed matter, 1955-1989 (Box-folder 4: 34-35)
      - Printed matter, 1992 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Northrup Aircraft, Inc., 1951-1954 (Box-folder 5: 2)
      See also: Oversize Material/Box 17, Folder 4.
    - U.S. Civil Service Commission, 1956 (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - Lockheed Missiles and Space Company
      - Employment, 1956-1985 (Box-folder 5: 4)
        Includes retirement papers. See also: Oversize Material/Box 17, Folder 6.
      - Projects
        - Polaris
          - Development, 1955-1962 (Box-folder 5: 5)
            See also: Photographs/Box 16, Folder 10, and Oversize Material/Box 17, Folder 1.
          - Clippings, 1960, undated (Box-folder 5: 6)
          - Histories, 1961-1986 (Box-folder 5: 7)
          - Printed matter, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 5: 8)
        - Project Starlight
          - Development, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 5: 9)
            Includes Institute of Defense Analyses employment paperwork.
          - Notebook, 1962 (Box-folder 5: 10)
          - Reference articles, 1960-1966 (Box-folder 5: 11)
        - Sub designs and studies, 1965-1971 (Box-folder 5: 12)
          See also: Oversize Material/Box 17, Folders 1 and 4, and Oversize Material/Large diagrams.
        - Poseidon, 1966 (Box-folder 5: 13)
        - STRAT-X
          - Development, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 5: 14-15)
            See also: Oversize Material/Box 17, Folder 5, and Oversize Material/Large diagrams.
          - Underwater long-range missile systems (ULMS), 1966-1968 (Box-folder 6: 1)
            See also: Oversize Material/Large diagrams.
          - ULMS notebook, 1967 (Box-folder 6: 2)
        - Power sources for propulsion, 1966-1975 (Box-folder 6: 3)
          Includes reference articles from 1961 and 1962.
        - Underwater shock, 1967 (Box-folder 6: 4)
          See also: Oversize Material/Box 17, Folder 5.
        - SSBN studies/weapon systems, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 6: 5)
          Includes reference articles from 1965. See also: Oversize Material/Box 17, Folder 1.
        - Modular multipurpose missile (MMM), 1971 (Box-folder 6: 6)
          See also: Oversize Material/Box 17, Folders 1 and 4, and Oversize Material/Large blueprints.
        - Underwater launch, 1971 (Box-folder 6: 7)
          See also: Oversize Material/Box 17, Folder 1.
        - Three tube - S5G concept, 1971 (Box-folder 6: 8)
        - Shelf deployment, 1971-1978 (Box-folder 6: 9)
        - Trident I, 1972 (Box-folder 6: 10)
        - Trident II, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 6: 11-12)
        - "Water Tunnel Tests of Hydrodynamic Control Devices for Trident II,", 1975 (Box-folder 7: 1)
        - Alternate SLBM basing, 1973 (Box-folder 7: 2)
        - Miscellaneous missile development, 1967-1974 (Box-folder 7: 3)
      - Newsletters and press releases, 1956-1975 (Box-folder 7: 4)
      - Printed matter, 1964-1994 (Box-folder 7: 5-9)
        Includes Lockheed Life magazine, 1977-1983.
    - Submersibles
      - Development, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 7: 10-12)
      - Noise, 1968 (Box-folder 7: 13)
      - Life support and manning, 1974 (Box-folder 7: 14)
      - Printed matter, 1963-1966 (Box-folder 7: 15)
    - Battery barge concepts, undated (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - Missile capsules, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 8: 2)
    - R & D Associates
      - Meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 8: 3)
      - Strategic Systems Study, 1974 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - Defense Science Board, 1974 (Box-folder 8: 5)
    - Engine study
      Fiedler had originally placed the papers for this study into a series of different colored folders. The list of folder titles with their corresponding colors appears at the beginning of the first folder. Not all of the folders were found, but for those that were, the original order and folder titles have been retained. The original color of each folder appears in brackets.
      - Controller types [Green], 1976-1979 (Box-folder 8: 6)
      - Preliminary studies I [Red], 1975-1976 (Box-folder 8: 7)
      - Preliminary studies II [Red], 1976-1978 (Box-folder 8: 8)
      - Stratified charge [Red], 1976 (Box-folder 8: 9)
      - Controller A tests [Yellow], 1976 (Box-folder 8: 10)
      - Controller B tests [Yellow], 1977 (Box-folder 8: 11)
      - Controller C tests [Yellow], 1977-1978 (Box-folder 8: 12)
      - Fuelmeter and vacuum drive tests [Yellow], 1976-1977 (Box-folder 8: 13)
      - Related system studies [Beige], 1975-1980 (Box-folder 8: 14)
      - Further notes, 1975-1979 (Box-folder 8: 15)
      - Notebook, undated (Box-folder 8: 16)
    - Large aircraft, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 8: 17)
    - Container aircraft, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
    - Altran Corporation
      - Employment, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 9: 3)
        Includes stocks paperwork and right of first refusal agreement.
      - Test methods and results, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 9: 4)
      - Projects, 1988-1992 (Box-folder 9: 5-6)
        Studies and experiments related to alpha decay. See also: Oversize Material/Box 17, Folders 2-3.
    - Unidentified projects, 1991, undated (Box-folder 9: 7)
    - Unidentified notes, undated (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Patents
    Includes patent applications, drafts, amendments, correspondence, allowances, certificates, and printed patents, arranged chronologically.
    - Split Aircraft Wing, 1952-1956 (Box-folder 9: 9)
      See also: Photographs/Box 16, Folder 4.
    - Bettsessel, 1953 (Box-folder 9: 10)
    - Jet Direction Control Device, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 9: 11)
    - Induced Pitch Launcher Device, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 9: 12)
    - Jet Deflector, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 9: 13)
    - Miscellaneous patents, 1956-1965 (Box-folder 9: 14)
      Patents include: Jet-Ignited Tracking Flare, Aerodynamic Optic Collector, Holdback Device for Missile Launching, Externally Mounted Jet-Ignited Tracking Flare, Self-Contained Data Recorder, and Deep Submergence Underwater Vehicle.
    - Fuel Control of Internal Combustion Engines
      - Original application, 1975 December (Box-folder 9: 15)
      - First examiner response, 1976 September (Box-folder 9: 16)
      - First amendment, 1976 December (Box-folder 10: 1)
      - Second examiner response, 1977 April (Box-folder 10: 2)
      - Second amendment, 1977 July (Box-folder 10: 3)
      - Allowance, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 10: 4)
      - Awarded patent, 1978 January (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - Fluiddynamic Control of Otto-Cycle Engines, 1978-1981 (Box-folder 10: 6)
    - Fuel Distribution in Internal Combustion Engines
      - Applications, 1977 (Box-folder 10: 7)
      - Examiner and amendment, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 10: 8)
      - Awarded patent, 1979 (Box-folder 10: 9)
    - Fuel Control and Injection System for Internal Combustion Engines
      - Applications, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 10: 10)
      - Awarded patent, industry contacts, 1981 (Box-folder 10: 11)
    - Aerodynamically Controlled Fuel Injection, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 10: 12)
    - Increasing Alpha Decay Rates Through the Use of Static and Time Varying Electric Fields and Magnetic Fields, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 10: 13)
- Speeches and Writings, 1958-1992
  - "The Launching of Large Missiles,", 1958 October 6 (Box-folder 10: 14)
  - "Alternatives for Sea-Based Missile Forces,", 1974 April 1 (Box-folder 10: 15)
    Co-authored by G. Aubert, J. Ericson, R. Could, J. Hurley, N. Kfoury, J. Mullin, F. Parry, and B. Werle.
  - "Fluiddynamic Fuel Control,", 1975 September 23
    - Rough drafts (Box-folder 10: 16)
    - Final drafts (Box-folder 10: 17)
  - "Aerodynamic Computation of Air Fuel Ratios"
    - Proposals and drafts, 1978 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Final drafts, undated (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - Conference paper, 1980 February 25-29 (Box-folder 11: 3)
      Society of Automotive Engineers Congress and Exposition in Detroit. Includes some correspondence from 1981.
  - "Altering Natural Alpha Decay Rates,", 1990 (Box-folder 11: 4)
    Abstract, drafts, and data. Co-authored by William A. Barker.
  - "Alpha and Fusion Power Generation,", 1992 January 13 (Box-folder 11: 5)
    Co-authored by William A. Barker.
- Writings by Others, 1933-1993
  - General
    - Unidentified, undated (Box-folder 11: 6)
    - A-F, 1954-1988 (Box-folder 11: 7)
    - G-K, 1944-1980 (Box-folder 11: 8)
    - L-W, 1958-1969 (Box-folder 11: 9)
  - Aerojet-General Corporation, "Capsule Feasibility Study,", 1963 June (Box-folder 11: 10)
  - American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AIAA) annual meeting papers, 1964-1978 (Box-folder 11: 11)
  - Arentzen, E. S. and Philip Mandel, "Naval Architectural Aspects of Submarine Design,", 1960 (Box-folder 11: 12)
  - Gates, David M., "Nuclear Power," Energy and Ecology, 1985 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Greil, Karl, "The Development of the Guided Anti Aircraft Rocket 'Oerlikon' in Switzerland,", 1951 (Box-folder 12: 2)
  - Jacobs, Eastman N., 1933-1937 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    "The Characteristics of 78 Related Airfoil Sections from Tests in the Variable-Density Wind Tunnel," 1933, and "Airfoil Section Characteristics as Affected by Variations of the Reynolds Number," 1937.
  - Members of Congress for Peace through Law, "Report on ULMS,", 1972 April 10 (Box-folder 12: 4)
  - Office of Naval Research papers, 1975 (Box-folder 12: 5)
  - Proppe, Tasso, 1975-1993 (Box-folder 12: 6)
  - Schneider, M. H. and E. E. Cook, "Study of a Deep Submergence Missile Capsule - Titanium (U),", 1963 June (Box-folder 12: 7)
  - Surface Effect Ships for Ocean Commerce (SESOC) Advisory Committee, "Final Report on a Study of the Technological Problems,", 1966 February (Box-folder 12: 8)
  - Wormeer, E. M., "Launching the A4 (V2) Rocket Missile at Sea,", 1946 August 7 (Box-folder 12: 9)
  - Ziegler, et. al., "Hochleistungssegelflugzeug FS 18,", 1938 (Box-folder 12: 10)
    Co-authored by Bälz, Körber, Läpple, and Söhne.
- Subject File, 1943-1992
  - Alte Rechliner
    - Membership and newsletters, 1964-1992 (Box-folder 12: 11)
    - "Rechliner Briefe," volumes 1 and 2, undated (Box-folder 12: 12-13)
    - "Rechliner Briefe," volumes 3 and 4, 1978 September - 1982 August (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
  - Altherrenschaft, 1951 (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - Barker, William A.
    - Writings, 1987-1992 (Box-folder 13: 4-5)
      Includes biographical note.
    - Theories, 1982 (Box-folder 13: 6-7)
      Contains two lists of original folder titles related to William Barker's scientific projects. Not all folders were found, but those that were have retained their original titles and order. See also: Oversize Material/Box 17, Folder 5.
    - Proposals, undated (Box-folder 13: 8)
    - Patents
      - Electrostatic Voltage Excitation Process and Apparatus, 1990 (Box-folder 13: 9)
      - Electrostatic Voltage Excitation Process and Apparatus, 1990 (Box-folder 14: 1)
      - Method for Enhancing Alpha Decay in Radioactive Materials, 1991 (Box-folder 14: 2)
    - Equipment/symbols, 1987, undated (Box-folder 14: 3)
  - Guidance computers, 1961-1966 (Box-folder 14: 4)
  - Motorsegler, 1978-1992 (Box-folder 14: 5)
    Includes materials on the European Motorsegler Championships. In English and German.
  - Nucell battery, 1988 (Box-folder 14: 6)
  - Reitsch, Hanna, 1954-1992 (Box-folder 14: 7)
  - Sailplanes, 1951-1985 (Box-folder 14: 8)
    See also: Oversize Material/Box 17, Folders 4 and 6.
  - Schempp-Hirth Kirchheim-Teck, 1943-1954 (Box-folder 14: 9)
  - Society of Automotive Engineers, 1980 (Box-folder 14: 10)
    Notes, correspondence, brochure, and conference paper for the Aerospace Congress and Exposition, 1980.
- Printed Matter, 1933-1994
  - Instructional material
    - "Bauvorschriften für Flugzeuge,", 1933 April (Box-folder 14: 11)
    - "Bauvorschriften für Segelflugzeuge,", 1939 August - 1940 February (Box-folder 14: 12-13)
    - "Vorlesungen über Flugzeugbau,", 1941 October - 1942 January (Box-folder 14: 14-15)
  - Informational material, 1949-1968 (Box-folder 14: 16)
    Informational brochures for a camera store owned by Fiedler's family in Freudenstadt, the U.S. Navy's fleet ballistic missile program, WWII suicide bombs, and fallout shelters. In English and German.
  - Informational material, 1975-1994 (Box-folder 15: 1)
    Informational brochures for the U.S. Navy's fleet ballistic missile program and the Naval Air Weapons Station in Point Mugu, California, and catalogues for experiment equipment.
  - Newsletters and journals
    - Ultra-Lite Aircraft Journal, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 15: 2)
    - Foreign Affairs, 1968 July - 1969 October (Box-folder 15: 3)
    - Scientific American, 1969 August - 1970 January (Box-folder 15: 4)
    - High Frontier, 1991 October - 1992 August (Box-folder 15: 5)
    - Die Rakete, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 15: 6)
    - Miscellaneous newsletters, 1973-1993 (Box-folder 15: 7)
  - Conference program, 1988 August 29 - September 2 (Box-folder 15: 8)
    Militärgeschichtliches Forschungsamt conference in Freiburg, titled "Der Internationalen Wissenschaftlichen Tagung," with the subject: "Luftkriegführung im Zweiten Weltkrieg. Ein Internationaler Vergleich."
  - Newspaper clippings, 1960-1992 (Box-folder 15: 9)
  - Magazine articles, 1938-1994 (Box-folder 15: 10-11)
  - Magazines, 1963-1989 (Box-folder 15: 12)
- Sound Recording, undated (Box 15)
  One untitled compact sound cassette.
- Videorecording, 1993 September 10 (Box 15)
  Access
  DVD access copy of this video is available in the Archives reading room. Use copy reference number: 95009_0001_r2015